A Guide to the Dell Upton Papers, 1973-1999
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Dell Upton Papers 1973-1999
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 1999.13
4 linear feet.
Upton, Dell
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1999
Biographical/Historical Information
Dell Upton, a graduate of Colgate University and Brown University, is currently Professor of Anthropology and Architecture at the University of Virginia. Previously he taught at the University of California, Berkelely. In his own words, "I study the material world as an aspect of human expressive culture. My research and publications have focused on architecture and cultural landscapes, which I see as subsets of material culture. Early in my career I worked on colonial American architecture, particularly the rural vernacular architecture of seventeenth- and eighteenth-century Virginia and New England. I was interested in the social-historical aspects of architecture as well as in theories of architectural design drawn from archaeology and linguistics." (Retrieved from http://www.virginia.edu/anthropology/faculty/upton.html, August 8, 2008)
Scope and Content
The papers, a part of the 20th Century Collections, are arranged in four subseries: Churches, Houses, Assorted, and Notebooks. The Churches subseries is arranged by topic, with the majority of the information pertaining to church buildings in Virginia. Those are listed alphabetically by location. The Houses subseries is also arranged alphabetically by location. Assorted contains a variety of information, arranged by topic. Upton's notes can be found in the Notebooks series, arranged by size and chronologically.
Arrangement
The files are arranged in series.
Index Terms
Persons:
Upton, Dell
Corporate Names:
Colonial Williamsburg
Subjects:
Architecture, domestic; Church architecture - Virginia.; Architecture, Colonial - Virginia.; Church decoration and ornament - Virginia; Historic buildings - Virginia
Geographical Names:
United States - Architecture - 18th Century; United States - Architecture - 19th Century; Virginia - Church history; Virginia - Religious life and customs.
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings; Notebooks
Contents List
- Papers
  - Churches (Box 1)
    - Articles
    - Behavior
    - Buildings
      - England
      - United States (non-Virginia)
      - Virginia
        - Alexandria
          - Christ Church
        - Bennett's Creek
          - Glebe Church
        - Buckingham County
          - Buckingham Baptist
        - Charles City County
          - Westover Church
        - Chuckatuck
          - St. John's
        - Culpeper
          - Little Fork Church
        - Essex County
          - Vauter's Church
        - Falls Church
          - Falls Church
        - Fairfax County
          - Pohick Church
          - Providence Presbyterian
        - Gloucester County
          - Abingdon Church
          - Ware Church
        - Hampton
          - St. John's Church
        - Hanover County
          - Fork Church
          - Slash Church
        - Hartfield
          - Lower United Methodist Church
        - Jamestown Island
          - Jamestown Church
        - King and Queen County
          - Mattaponi Church
          - Stratton Major Church
        - King George County
          - Lambs Creek Church
          - St. Paul's Church
        - King William County
          - Mangohick Baptist Church
          - St. John's Church
        - Lancaster
          - Christ Church
          - St. Mary's White Chapel
        - Middlesex County
          - Christ Church
        - New Kent County
          - St. Peter's Church
        - Norfolk
          - St. Paul's Church
        - Petersburg
          - Blandford Church
        - Prince George County
          - Merchant's Hope Church
        - Princess Anne County
          - Old Donation Church
        - Richmond
          - St. John's Church
        - Richmond Courthouse
          - Farnham Church
        - Smithfield
          - St. Luke's Church
        - Stafford County
          - Aquia Church
        - Surry County
          - Lower Southwark Church
        - Westmoreland County
          - Yeocomico Church
        - Westover
          - Lower Church
        - Williamsburg
          - Bruton Parish Church
          - William and Mary Chapel
        - General, (3 folders) (Box 2)
        - Notes and critiques
        - Ornaments and fittings
        - Pulpits, altarpieces, and fonts
        - Vestry books
        - Virginia Gazette, Prints and transcripts
  - Houses
    - Delaware
      - Log House, National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institution
    - Massachusetts
      - Dorchester
        - Pierce House
    - New York
      - Hall-Christie House, Dutchess County, New York
    - Rhode Island (Box 3)
      - General
      - Mott House
      - Warwick
        - James Green House
    - Virginia
      - Arlington County
        - Ball-Sellers House
      - August a County
      - Bowling Green
        - Old Mansion
      - Brunswick County
      - Charles City County
        - Westover
      - Chesterfield County
        - Brown-Boveri House
      - Courtland
        - Mahone Tavern
      - Fauquier County
        - The Hollow
      - Fort Royal
        - Powers Buggy Shop
      - Fredricksburg
        - Mary Washington House
      - Goochland County
        - Tuckahoe
      - Hanover County
        - Doswell House
        - Springfield Farm
      - Isle of Wight County
        - Eley House
        - Four Square
        - Henry Saunders House (Box 4)
        - Turner House and Kitchen
      - King and Queen County
        - Little Plymouth
      - King George County
        - Marmion House
      - King William County
        - Sweet Hall
      - Lancaster County
        - 17th century
        - 18th century
        - 19th century
        - Norwood House
      - Lunenburg
        - Flatrock
      - Newport News
        - Miles Cary Site
      - Prince Edward County
      - Pulaski County
      - Richmond County
        - Linden Farm
      - Rockeridge County
      - Shenandoah County
      - Southampton
        - 18th century
        - 19th century
        - Bowen's House
        - Buzzard's Nest
        - Hodges Farm
        - Lankford House
        - Snowden House
        - Sunnyside
        - Walnut Hill
      - Surry
        - Bacon's Castle
        - James House
        - May nard House
        - Rich Neck House
        - Walnut Valley
      - Virginia Beach
        - 19th century houses
      - Westmoreland County
        - 18th century houses
        - 19th century houses
      - Yorktown
        - Article and notes
        - Ballard House
        - Courthouse
        - Customs House
        - Digges House
        - Moore House (Box 5)
        - Nelson House
        - Pate House
        - Shield House
        - Smith House
        - Somerwell House
        - Swan Tavern
        - General
  - Assorted
    - Board Notes, 1975
    - Chesapeake Farm Buildings Survey
    - CW Forge Project (Anderson Forge)
    - CW Store project (Box 6)
    - Dutch, field notes
    - German Virginia
      - Notes
      - Plans and photos
    - Inventories
    - NTP Field notes
    - Post Building
    - Reference, Maps and charts
    - Traditional framing
    - Miscellaneous
  - Notebooks (Box 7)
    - Large notebooks
      - Virginia 1, Notes 3, September 9, 1974-March11, 1975
      - Virginia 2, Notes 4, March8, 1975-May 22, 1975
      - Virginia 3, Notes 5, June 10, 1975-August 17, 1975
      - Virginia 4, Notes 6, August 18, 1975-January 18, 1976
      - Virginia 5, Notes 7January 26, 1976-May 7, 1976
      - Virginia 6, Notes 7AMay 3, 1976-August 31, 1976
      - Notes 8A (non-Virginia), May 23, 1976
      - Virginia 7, Notes 8September 21, 1976-February25, 1977
      - Virginia 8, Notes 9, March17, 1977-June 21, 1977
      - Virginia 9 Notes 10, June 23, 1977-November 25, 1977
      - Notes 11, December 7, 1977-June 22, 1978
      - Virginia 12, June 26, 1978-October 13, 1978
      - Virginia 13, October 20, 1973
    - Steno books
      - Mott Farm Removal, 1973
      - Field Notes 1, New England
      - Working notebook 21974 (Box 8)
      - Steno 1
      - Book II (rough notes), May 15, 1975
      - Book III, n.d.
      - Book IV, n.d.
      - Book V (Norfolk survey), November 29, 1975
      - Book VI, May 7, 1976-June 12, 1976
      - Book VII, July 16, 1976-October 9, 1976
      - Book VIII, October 13, 1976
      - Book VIIII, January 15, 1977
      - Book X, n.d.
      - Book XI, May 10, 1977
      - Book XII, June 21, 1977
      - Book XIII, July 21, 1977-September 14, 1977
      - Book XIIII, August 1977-December 29, 1977
      - Book XV, November 25, 1977
      - Book XVI, February9, 1978-June 22, 1978
      - Book XVII, June 26, 1978
      - Book XVIII, August 1978
      - Book XIX, September 15, 1978
      - Book XX, January 11, 1979
      - Book XXI, February 17, 1979
      - Book XXI, n.d.
      - Book XXIII, n.d.
      - Untitled, n.d.